A Guide to the Record Group Vertical Files, 1960s-present
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
- Record Group 9 - University Council
  - RG 9/2 - Commission on Graduate Studies and Policies (CGSP)
    Originally named the Graduate Committee, the group became the Commission on Research and Graduate Studies on October 7, 1969. The name was changed to the Commission on Graduate Studies and Research on August 30, 1973, then became the Commission on Graduate Studies on October 6, 1982, when the Commission on Research [RG 9/2/1] was established. It later became the Commission on Graduate Studies and Policies (CGSP).
    - RG 9/2/1 - Commission on Research
      The Commission on Research developed out of the Commission on Graduate Studies and Research [RG 9/2] in October 1982.
    - RG 9/2/2 - Advisory Committee on Pre-Medical/Dental/Veterinary
      See also RG 5/2/5.
  - RG 9/3 - Commission on Student Affairs
    The Student Activities Committee was founded in 1947. On September 29, 1969, it was renamed the Commission on Undergraduate Student Affairs, becoming the Commission on Student Affairs on August 20, 1970.
    May include Campus Girl Scouts; Sigma Delta Psi (athletic honorary) [see RG 9/3 minutes of 1/24/1975 Sect. 5a]; Zero Population Growth; Harmony (organization involving different fellowships on campus) [see RG 9/3 minutes of 1/24/1975, Sect. 5c]; Triangle Fraternity (architecture) [see RG 9/3, 1/24/1975]
    - RG 9/3a - Student Budget Board
      May include Student organization funding; Greek Affairs Subcommittee; Student Constitutional Affairs Board
  - RG 9/4 - Commission on Undergraduate Studies
    May include University Forum on Liberal Education; Commission Forum on Liberal Education; Grades and Grading
    - RG 9/4a - Core Curriculum
      May include Curriculum for Liberal Education (CLE)
    - RG 9/4b - Upward Bound/Talent Search
  - RG 9/5 - Commission on Extension and Public Service
  - RG 9/6 - Commission on Classified Staff Affairs
  - RG 9/7 - University Advisory Council on Strategic Budgeting and Planning
  - RG 9/8 - Commission on Equal Opportunity and Diversity
    May include Women's Alliance
  - RG 9/9 - Commission on Administrative and Professional Faculty Affairs
- Record Group 10 - Department of Athletics
  "While some sports were played in the early days of the College, the first formal effort to organize campus sports was in 1891 with the formation of the Athletic Association. In 1901, the president appointed a faculty committee to administer the expanding athletic program. Then, a reorganization plan entrusted control of athletics to three committees: an advisory council, executive committee, and a faculty committee on athletics.
  In 1904, the general manager position was created, along with an Athletic Council to control college athletics. The Athletic Council governed the body of athletics, and the Athletic Association was the operating organization and a non-stock corporation under state law until 1990. In 1990, Virginia Tech athletics were reorganized and put under the direct control of the university.
  The Association founded the student newspaper The Virginia Tech (later the Collegiate Times) [RG 31/17] in 1903 and operated it as their official organ until the student body assumed control in 1931. The Association also owned and operated the College Bookstore from 1911 until 1968 when VPI Facilities, Inc. [RG 6/6], assumed control."
  May include Blueprint Committee; Student-Athlete Pylons of Promise, #LOVE Initiative
  See also RG 8/6/1 for Sports Medicine.
  - RG 10 - Department of Athletics (Publications) [items also in Oversize Box 1]
  - RG 10a - Athletic Controversies
  - RG 10a - Athletic Scandal
  - RG 10b - Fundraising and Finances
  - RG 10/1 - Baseball [items also in Oversize Box 1]
    The first baseball game was in 1877 against Roanoke College. However, the sport did not become organized on a regular basis until 1892.
  - RG 10/2 - Basketball [items also in Oversize Folder 1 and Oversize Box 1]
    Virginia Tech's first basketball game was played on January 22, 1909, in the Stone Auditorium (later Chapel and then the Library) against Emory and Henry.
    This primarily focuses on Men's Basketball, but may contain Women's Basketball. May include Bill Roth's Kids Day; 1973 N.I.T. championship
    See also RG 10/5g/1 for Women's Basketball.
    - RG 10/2 - Basketball, 1979-1989
    - RG 10/2 - Basketball, 1989-1999
    - RG 10/2 - Basketball, 1999-2000
    - RG 10/2 - Basketball scandal, 1987
  - RG 10/3 - Football [items also in Oversize Folder 1 and Oversize Box 1]
    In the fall of 1891, a few students gathered and played the first game of Rugby football at VPI in a field behind Number One Barracks (later Lane Hall). In September 1892, two teams were organized, and Dean Ellison A. Smyth was made the first coach and manager.
    - RG 10/3 - Football, pre-1980
    - RG 10/3 - Football, 1980-1989
    - RG 10/3 - Football, 1990-1999
    - RG 10/3 - Football, 2000-present
    - RG 10/3 - Football (Publications)
    - RG 10/3a - Virginia Tech - VMI Rivalry
    - RG 10/3b - Bowl Games [items also in Oversize Box 1]
    - RG 10/3c - Virginia Tech - University of Virginia (UVA) rivalry
      May include Commonwealth Cup
    - RG 10/3d - Football Camp [items also in Oversize Box 1]
  - RG 10/4 - Wrestling [items also in Oversize Box 1]
    A wrestling club was formed in 1910, and wrestling was made a varsity sport in 1922.
  - RG 10/5 - Miscellaneous Sports (Minor Sports)
    - RG 10/5a - Golf [items also in Oversize Box 1]
    - RG 10/5b - Gymnastics
    - RG 10/5c - Soccer [items also in Oversize Box 1]
    - RG 10/5d - Swimming and diving [items also in Oversize Box 1]
    - RG 10/5e - Tennis, Men's [items also in Oversize Box 1]
      This primarily focuses on Men's Tennis, but may contain Women's Tennis.
      See also RG 10/5g/3 for Women's Tennis.
    - RG 10/5f - Track and Field
      - RG 10/5f/1 - Cross-country track [items also in Oversize Box 1]
    - RG 10/5g - Women's Intercollegiate Sports
      May include Women's Varsity Club; Celebration of Women's Sports Luncheon
      - RG 10/5g/1 - Basketball, Women's [items also in Oversize Box 1]
        This primarily focuses on Women's Basketball, but may contain Men's Basketball.
        See also RG 10/5e for Men's Basketball, which may contain some Women's Basketball.
        - RG 10/5g/1 - Basketball (Information)
        - RG 10/5g/1 - Basketball (Publications, General)
        - RG 10/5g/1a - Basketball (Publications, Season Guides/Programs)
        - RG 10/5g/1b - Basketball (Publications, Game Programs)
      - RG 10/5g/2 - Field Hockey
      - RG 10/5g/3 - Tennis, Women's [items also in Oversize Box 1]
        This primarily focuses on Women's Tennis, but may contain Men's Tennis.
        See also RG 10/5e for Men's Tennis, which may contain some Women's Tennis.
      - RG 10/5g/4 - Volleyball [items also in Oversize Box 1]
      - RG 10/5g/5 - Lacrosse [see also RG 10/13/2] [items also in Oversize Folder 1]
      - RG 10/5g/6 - Softball [see also RG 10/13/5]
    - RG 10/5h - Boxing [obsolete]
    - RG 10/5i - Monogram Club
  - RG 10/6 - Student Aid Association
    May include Meritorious Service Award
    - RG 10/6a - Hokie Club
      May include Keep Jumping Fund
  - RG 10/7 - Athletics Director
    - RG 10/7/1 - Recruiting
    - RG 10/7/2 - Schedules
    - RG 10/7/3 - Marketing and media
      May include ACC Network studios; Television; Radio; Newspapers; Sports Information
  - RG 10/8 - Athletic Board
    The Athletic Board was formerly Athletic Council.
    See also RG 40.
  - RG 10/9 - All-Sports Camp
  - RG 10/10 - Coaching Clinic, Virginia High School League (VHSL), Virginia High School Coaching Association (VHCA) [items also in Oversize Box 1]
  - RG 10/11 - Miscellaneous
    May include hokiesports.com; All Sports Banquet; Athletics student interns
    - RG 10/11a - Mascot (Football) [items also in Oversize Box 1]
      May include HokieBird
      See also RG 40/1.
    - RG 10/11b - Governor's Day
    - RG 10/11c - Fan Support
      May include Hokie Kids' Club
    - RG 10/11d - Athletics and Academics
      May include Student athletes [see also RG 5/18]
    - RG 10/11e - Drug Testing (includes steroids)
  - RG 10/12 - Southern Conference [obsolete, 1965]
  - RG 10/13 - Metro Conference (including Conference's affiliations)
    - RG 10/13/1 - Intramural Sports, 1960
    - RG 10/13/2 - Lacrosse, 1968 [obsolete; see RG 10/5g/5]
    - RG 10/13/3 - Racquetball
    - RG 10/13/4 - Rugby, 1966 [obsolete; see RG 31/15 for Rugby Clubs]
    - RG 10/13/5 - Softball, 1960-1964 [obsolete; see RG 10/5g/6]
    - RG 10/13/6 - Weightlifting, 1960
  - RG 10/14 - Big East Conference
  - RG 10/15 - Hall of Fame
  - RG 10/16 - Atlantic Coast Conference (ACC)
  - RG 10/17 - National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA)
    May include Academic Progress Rate (APR); NCAA rule violations
  - RG 10/18 - Spirit Squads / Spirit Programs
    May include Cheerleading; HighTechs
- Record Group 11 - Dean of the College [obsolete, 1949]
  In 1919, the president reorganized the college. Part of the reorganization was the elimination of the deanships of the general faculty, the graduate department [RG 22], the academic department, and the applied science department. To replace these deanships, the position of Dean of the College was established.
  A Dean of Students position [RG 8] was created in 1923 and abolished the next year, when the Dean of the College assumed those responsibilities officially and unofficially shared the responsibilities with the Secretary of the YMCA [RG 31/10/26]. From 1926-1937, the duties of the Registrar [RG 5/2/2] were handled by the Assistant to the Dean of the College.
  The position was abolished in 1949.
  May include Physical Education Intramural and Water Carnival
- Record Group 12 - School of Applied Science and Business Administration [obsolete, 1962]
  The Department of Business Administration was established in 1924, and the School of Applied Science and Business Administration was formed in 1950 out of the Department. In 1960, the School dissolved, and several departments moved to the School of Business (later the College of Business [RG 16]) and the School of Science and General Studies (later College of Arts and Sciences [RG15]).
  See also RG 16.
  - RG 12 - School of Applied Science and Business Administration (Information and Publications)
- Record Group 13 - College of Agriculture and Life Sciences (CALS)
  Agricultural training was one of the primary missions of the university from its beginnings. In the 1872 Catalog, Agriculture is listed as one of 13 courses of study, which would today be considered departments. The Department of Agriculture was one of the first four major administrative divisions created when Deans were appointed to the academic departments. In 1907, a School of Scientific Agriculture and a School of Agricultural Apprentices were established within the Department of Agriculture. In 1920, the title was changed to School of Agriculture, becoming the College of Agriculture in 1964. The name was changed to the College of Agriculture and Life Sciences in 1971.
  May include Bremo Plantation; Cephisus [Horticulture]; Certificates of Merit - Agriculture, 1923-1954; Holy Cross Abbey; Virginia Agriculture Leaders Obtaining Results (VALOR); Virginia State College (Petersburg) merger controversy; Virginia Livestock Hall of Fame; Virginia Tech Postbaccalaureate Research and Education Program (VT-PREP); Agency 229
  - RG 13 - College of Agriculture and Life Sciences (CALS) (Information)
  - RG 13 - College of Agriculture and Life Sciences (CALS) (Publications)
  - RG 13a - Events
    May include Seminars; Guest Speakers; Conferences; Commencement﻿
  - RG 13/1 - Office of the Dean
  - RG 13/2 - Individual Faculty
    May include General Education Board
    - RG 13/2/1 - Counselors
  - RG 13/3 - Department of Agricultural and Applied Economics
    Courses in agricultural economics began in 1921. In 1924, the Department of Agricultural Economics was established. The department has been renamed several times: Agricultural Economics and Rural Sociology (1929-1933), Agricultural Economics (1933-1940), Department of Agricultural Economics, Rural Sociology, and Statistics (1946-1948), Agricultural Economics and Rural Sociology (1948-1965), and Agricultural Economics (1965-1993. It became the Department of Agricultural and Applied Economics in August 1993.
    May include Electronic Farm Record Program; Farm Survey Worksheets (1930-1940); Center for Economic Education; Center for Agricultural Trade
  - RG 13/4 - Department of Biological Systems Engineering (BSE)
    Courses in agricultural engineering were offered as early as 1912. In 1919, the Department of Agricultural Engineering was established, and the first bachelors degree in Agricultural Engineering was offered in 1921. The department became the Department of Biological Systems Engineering (BSE) in 1992. It is housed within both the College of Agriculture and Life Sciences and the College of Engineering.
    May include Mechanical Apple Pickers; Virginia Household Water Quality Program
    See also RG 18/4.
    - RG 13/4/1 - Cyrus McCormick Farm (Walnut Grove)
  - RG 13/5 - Department of Agronomy [obsolete, 1987; see RG 13/14]
    Agronomy courses have been taught since 1872. The Department of Agronomy was established in 1907, and the first bachelor degree in Agronomy was awarded in 1921. The Department of Agronomy became the Department of Crop and Soil Environmental Sciences [RG 13/14] in 1987.
    May include Soil Testing Laboratory; Turfgrass research
  - RG 13/6 - Department of Animal Science [obsolete, July 1993; see RG 13/23]
    Courses pertaining to animal science were first offered in 1872. The first bachelors degree in animal science was given in 1921. The department was known as Animal Husbandry from 1908 to 1963, when it became the Department of Animal Science. In July 1993, it merged with the Department of Poultry Science [RG 13/13] to become Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences [RG 13/23].
    May include Animal Nutrition Colloquium
  - RG 13/7 - Department of Biochemistry
    Formerly called the Department of Biochemistry and Nutrition, the Department of Biochemistry is within both the College of Agriculture and Life Sciences (CALS) and College of Science (COS). It was previously a joint program [RG 15/4] between CALS and the College of Arts and Sciences (CAS), which dissolved in 2003.
    See also RG 15/4.
  - RG 13/8 - Department of Dairy Science
    May include Dairy Cow Judging Team
  - RG 13/9 - Department of Entomology
    May include Hokie BugFest; Hokie Bug Camp; Virginia Tech Pesticide Programs (VTPP)
  - RG 13/10 - Department of Food Science and Technology
    May include Virginia Tech brewhouse; Center for Applied Health Sciences; Fermentation Program
    - RG 13/10/1 - Sea Grant Program
  - RG 13/11 - Department of Horticulture
    In 2018, the Department of Horticulture became part of the School of Plant and Environmental Sciences [RG 13/26] within the college.
    May include Thomas M. Brooks Forest Products Center [obsolete; see RG 45/4]; Horticulture Short Courses; Garden Lover's Short Course; Flower Show School; Florist's Short Course; Landscape Design School (short course); Homefield Farm [see also RG 13/21; RG 8/2/1j]
    - RG 13/11/1 - Hahn Horticulture Garden
      The Hahn Horticulture Garden was formerly the Horticulture Garden.
  - RG 13/12 - Department of Plant Pathology, Physiology, and Weed Sciences
    In 2018, the Department of Plant Pathology, Physiology, and Weed Sciences became part of the School of Plant and Environmental Sciences [RG 13/26] within the college.
    May include Translational Plant Sciences program
    See also RG 13/26.
    - RG 13/12/1 - Air Pollution Laboratory
  - RG 13/13 - Department of Poultry Science [obsolete, July 1993; see RG 13/23]
    The Department of Poultry Science was formerly called the Department of Poultry Husbandry. In July 1993, it merged with the Department of Animal Science to become Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences.
  - RG 13/14 - Department of Crop and Soil Environmental Science [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    The Department of Crop and Soil Environmental Science developed out of the Department of Agronomy [RG 13/5] in 1987. In 2018, the department became part of the School of Plant and Environmental Sciences [RG 13/26] within the college.
    May include Turfgrass Research Center; That Place That People Talk About Monacan-Tutelo Native Garden
    See also RG 13/5; RG 13/26.
  - RG 13/15 - Anaerobic Bacteriology Laboratory
    Administrative Note
    The Anaerobic Bacteriology Laboratory, also called Anaerobe Lab, was founded in 1970 and closed in 1995.
    May include Microbiology
    See also RG 13/7; RG 25/16.
  - RG 13/17 - Council of Agricultural Presidents (CAPS)
  - RG 13/18 - Biobased Materials Center
  - RG 13/19 - International Agriculture
  - RG 13/20 - Agricultural Technology Program [items also in Oversize Box 2]
  - RG 13/21 - Virginia Tech Research Farms [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    May include Kentland Farm; Farm and Family Showcase; SmartFarm Innovation Network; Homefield Farm [see also RG 13/11; RG 8/2/1j]
  - RG 13/22 - Alumni Organization
    May include CALS Alumni Awards
  - RG 13/23 - Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences
    In July 1993, the Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences formed out of the merger of the Department of Animal Science and the Department of Poultry Science.
    May include Meat Science Center; National Thanksgiving Turkeys
  - RG 13/24 - Department of Human Nutrition, Foods, and Exercise (HNFE)
    See also RG 19/4.
  - RG 13/25 - Department of Agricultural, Leadership, and Community Education
    Established in 1918, Agricutlural Education was taught in the Department of Agriculture (later the College of Agriculture and Life Sciences (CALS) [RG 13]). Agricutlural Education was renamed the Department of Vocational Education in 1935. It became part of the Division of Vocational and Technical Education [RG 17/6] in the College of Education [RG 17] when it formed in 1971.
    In 1991, the department returned to CALS. In 2001, the Agricultural Education program merged with the Extension Program and Development Unit to form the Department of Agricultural and Extension Education. The department was renamed Department of Agricultural, Leadership, and Community Education in 2014.
    See also RG 17/6; RG 17/6/1.
  - RG 13/26 - School of Plant and Environmental Sciences
    The School of Plant and Environmental Sciences was formed in 2018 with the Department of Horticulture [RG 13/11]; Department of Plant Pathology, Physiology, and Weed Sciences [RG 13/12]; and Department of Crop and Soil Environmental Science [RG 13/14].
  - RG 13/27 - CALS Global Programs
- Record Group 14 - College of Architecture and Urban Studies (CAUS)
  May include College of Architecture and Urban Studies (CAUS) Diversity Committee
  - RG 14 - College of Architecture and Urban Studies (CAUS) (Information)
  - RG 14 - College of Architecture and Urban Studies (CAUS) (Publications) [items also in Oversize Folder 1 and Oversize Box 2]
  - RG 14a - Faculty Newsletter
  - RG 14/1 - Office of the Dean
  - RG 14/2 - Individual Faculty
  - RG 14/3 - School of Architecture + Design
    In 2003, the School of Architecture + Design was formed by merging the Department of Architecture and Industrial (or Environmental) Design in CAUS and the Interior Design program [RG 19/8] formerly in the College of Human Sciences and Education [RG 19].
    May include Center for Design Research [see also RG 14/8]; Vibrations Testing Lab; Industrial Design Program; Center for High Performance Environments; University Innovation Fellows; International Archive of Women in Architecture Center [see also RG 23h/6/1; RG 23/7]
    See also RG 14/8.
    - RG 14/3/1 - Architecture
      Courses in architecture were listed in the college catalog as early as 1873. Courses were offered in the Architectural Engineering Department from 1928 through 1947, when the name changed to the Architecture Department.
      May include Department of Architectural Engineering
    - RG 14/3/2 - Landscape Architecture
    - RG 14/3/3 - Curriculum in Building Construction [obsolete; see RG 14/13]
      Courses in Building Construction were first offered in 1947 in the Architecture Department. The first bachelors degree in Building Construction was offered the next year. The Building Construction Department became part of the Myers-Lawson School of Construction [RG 14/13], which was founded in 2006.
    - RG 14/3/4 - Interior Design
      Interior Design was housed in the Department of Housing, Interior Design, and Resource Management [RG 19/8] in the College of Human Resources and Education [RG 19], until it dissolved in 2003. The program moved to the newly formed School of Architecture + Design [RG 14/3].
      See also RG 19/8.
  - RG 14/4 - Department of Environmental and Urban Systems
  - RG 14/5/1 - Urban and Regional Planning Graduate Program [obsolete; see RG 14/12]
    May include Center for Urban and Regional Studies [obsolete]
  - RG 14/6 - International Center for Regional Environmental Management and Planning (ICREMP)
  - RG 14/7 - Center for European Studies and Architecture (CESA) [obsolete; see RG 35/1/3]
    The Center for European Studies and Architecture (CESA) was founded in 1992. In 2014, it was renamed Steger Center for International Scholarship [RG 35/1/3]. The center was also called the European Studies Center.
  - RG 14/8 - Smart Houses
    May include Lumenhaus; FutureHAUS [see also RG 6/3/2b for Prices Fork Research Station 2017 fire]; TreeHAUS; U.S. Department of Energy Solar Decathlon Design Challenge; Center for Design Research [see also RG 14/3]
    See also RG 14/3.
  - RG 14/9/2 - 50th Anniversary of CAUS (2014)
  - RG 14/10 - School of Visual Arts (SOVA) [items also in Oversize Box 2]
    Various drawing courses have been offered at Virginia Tech since 1872. In 1967, a curriculum in Art was developed and administered jointly by the College of Arts and Sciences [RG 15] and the College of Architecture [RG 14]. The Art Department [RG 15/3] was established in the College of Arts and Sciences in 1976 and then became the Department of Art and Art History in 1983. The department joined the Division of Performing Arts to form the School of the Arts in the College of Arts and Sciences.
    In July 2003, the College of Arts and Sciences dissolved, and the School of the Arts became cross-collegial when the Department of Art and Art History moved to the College of Architecture and Urban Studies (CAUS), while the other departments joined the College of Liberal Arts and Human Sciences (CLAHS) [RG 48]. In 2008, the Department of Art and Art History separated from the other departments to become the School of Visual Arts in CAUS.
    May include The Armory Art Gallery; Creative Technologies Program; Visual Design Studio Center
    See also RG 15/3.
  - RG 14/11 - Program in Real Estate [obsolete, 2017; see RG 16/16]
    Established in 2013, the Program in Real Estate is an interdisciplinary program, affiliated with five colleges. In 2017, the program became an academic unit [RG 16/16] in the Pamplin College of Business [RG 16] in collaboration with the Myers-Lawson School of Construction [RG 14/13].
    See also RG 14/13; RG 16/16.
  - RG 14/12 - School of Public and International Affairs (SPIA)
    May include Department of Urban Affairs and Planning; Institute for Policy and Governance; Community Change Collaborative [formerly Community Voices]; Department of Government and International Affairs; Washington Semester in Global Engagement; Virginia Management Fellows; Global Forum on Urban and Regional Resilience [see also RG 5/21]